What is the difference between
bacti and
tantra? Tantra is a form of
bacti. Tantra is a type of
bacti. In
bi you believe that I am the embodied
soul and he is the supreme
soul. that there is
no match between the
two, that I will forever remain polluted
and he or goddess
she which is just a matter of saying
there is no difference will forever
remain
unpolluted most pure param buddha most
awake and most pure paramud nity forever
pure
forever, forever awake, enlightened,
forever
pure. Just like you cannot dissolve
uh a
rock in milk or water, bacti says I am
too impure to be
dissolved. So I am going to serve God.
BTI is purely about
service that I am going to
serve and I'm going to serve as a
friend. I'm going to serve as a servant.
I'm going to serve like a servant would
serve his or her
master. That's bi in a nutshell. True
bacti will always keep you
humble, will keep you grounded, will
keep you centered, will keep you real.
It would give you peace because you
believe I don't have to do everything
myself. There is a master who's looking
after
me that I don't have to have the burden
of doing everything on my own, fixing
everything on my own. I have a master. I
have a god who's doing that.
Tantra on the other hand says no
question about it that you are
supreme that you're very superior that
you're very
special
but
I am made from
you. I am a part of you. If I'm a part
of
you, then it must be possible by
definition for me to rise to such level
of purity someday, some point of time in
my life when I will be able to merge in
you.
But I am not interested in merging after
death.
I don't care about any liberation,
salvation, any moa, any nirvana after
I'm dead. I very much would like it when
I'm alive.
Therefore, I'm going to keep calling out
to
you, rising above my base fears, my
primal
fears and primal emotions of uh
ignorance, lust, hatred, jealousy, envy,
ego, anger, and so on. I'm going to keep
purifying myself and keep calling out to
you till one such day that you show
yourself to me.
And the moment I see you, I will become
you. That's the fundamental difference
between bi and tantra.
[Music]